



R .PRAVEEN KUMAR

Address:

#123 J.P nagar 6th phase, 7th cross K.R Layout Bangalore-560078 **Ph no:** 09731581657

e-mail:

r.praveen88@rediffmail.com

Professional Summary

 A self-taught Java programmer with 4+ years of experience working on various web based client server and distributed web applications currently working at Happiest Minds Technologies Pvt Ltd.

 Proficient in working with open source frameworks such as Spring 3.0, JSF 2.0, Hibernate 3.6 and Spring RESTful.

• With knowledge of Data structures and Algorithms, Object Oriented Programming, Design Patterns.

Team player with good analytical and communication skills. Enthusiastic and highly motivated.

Programming Skills

Languages Java (proficient), JavaScript & JQuery (prior experience), SQL (proficient), Unix

shell programming (proficient)

UI Frameworks HTML5 & CSS3 , Angular 2, Bootstrap 4 (prior experience)

Client/Server Technologies

Servlet 2.5 and JSP 2.0 (proficient)

Web Frameworks SpringMVC (proficient), JSF 2.0 (proficient), Spring 3.0 (proficient)

ORM Technologies Hibernate 3.6 (proficient), JPA 2.0 (prior experience)

Distributed Technologies

REST (prior experience), Spring RESTful (proficient)

experience), TOAD 9.6, MySQL Yog (prior experience)

Testing tools JUnit 4 (prior experience), Mockito (proficient)

Database & Connectivity

Oracle 10g, MySQL 5.5, PostgreSQL 9.5 (prior experience), JDBC 4.0 (proficient)

Application Servers JBoss 7.0, Tomcat 8 (prior experience)

Search Elastic Search 2.3.3, Log stash 1.1, Kibana 4.5 (prior experience)

Frameworks

System Tortoise SVN 1.6.7(proficient), Jira (prior experience), Jenkins (prior

Configuration tools experience), Git (proficient)

Operating Systems Windows 7, Linux (Cent OS 6.2, RHEL 5.x & 6.x) (prior experience)

Work Experience

Dana Aftermarket

Happiest Minds Technologies Pvt Ltd (http://www.happiestminds.com/)

(30,March2016 - Current)

Description

Worked on Dana Aftermarket an ecommerce platform for purchase of automotive parts manufactured by Dana Inc.

Roles & responsibilities

- Worked on the server side and search, data ingestion and shopper module of the project.
 - Coded end to end RESTful API's for the shopper module from the scratch using Spring framework and JPA.
 - Implemented a prototype dashboard using ElasticSearch, LogStash and Kibana.
 - Implemented API's using Spring and Apache POI library to parse excel sheets containing information about standards for the data ingestion module.
 - Configured Amazon SES (Simple Email Service) to send emails via the application.
 - Implemented Email API's and Email templates using Velocity framework and Amazon SES.
 - Wrote test cases using Junit and Mockito framework.

UFM (User File Management Service)

Happiest Minds Technologies Pvt Ltd (http://www.happiestminds.com/)

(15,July2015 - 30,March2016)

Description

Worked on UFM a tool used to manage media, documents, record and save screen casts.

Roles & responsibilities

- Worked on the file upload and screen capture module of the project.
 - Re-factored client side JavaScript code to perform chunked file upload.
 - Implemented recursion based retry mechanism for upload of failed fragments in JavaScript.
 - Used Java 1.7 concurrency support and executors framework to implement a retry mechanism for failed fragment upload in the existing chunked upload framework.
 - Implemented API Governance practices like Correlation Id and Health check.
 - Re-factored copy course function in UFM to fix bugs and defects.
 - Worked on POC for using Alfresco a content management solution; Implemented solutions for uploading files, changing meta-data, performing text based search of the repository.
 - Implemented shell scripts to support automated server patching.

Avaya Diagnostic Server (2.0 & 2.5)

Betsol Software India Pvt Ltd (http://www.betsol.com/) (3,Oct2013 – 30,June2015)

Description

Worked on Avaya Diagnostic Server (ADS 2.0 & ADS 2.5) a diagnostic product suite from Avaya containing SAL Gateway and SLAMon.

Roles & responsibilities

- Worked on the Installer of Avaya Diagnostic Server product suite
 - Wrote scripts to perform pre installation checks on the host for validating system and hardware requirements.
 - Implemented a command line utility "installslamonkeystore" to install keystore and

- encrypt keystore passwords.
- Implemented a command line utility "installdemocert" to automate the process of installing demo certificates to use SLAMon.
- Implemented a CLI utility "weblm_password" for granting service technicians access to WebLM licensing server.
- Implemented modularization of the service pack installer scripts and setup a service pack build distribution server to optimize the process for service pack releases.
- Worked on scripts for security hardening of the Linux distribution used and fixed tomcat vulnerabilities.
- Migrated the application SLAMon 2.5 (ServiceLevelAgreement Monitor) from Tomcat 6 to the latest version of Tomcat 7.
- Worked on creation of OVA packages of the ADS Installer using VMWare Studio and tested the deployments on Vcenter and ESXI hosts.
- Implemented changes to existing pom.xml and build.xml files for modularization of the installer.

Education

R.V College of Engineering, Bangalore

B.E (2006-2010)

Major: Biotechnology Aggregate: 75 %

Certifications and Training

- Completed **Oracle certified Associate** (OCAJP7) and **Oracle certified Professional Java programmer** exam (OCPJP7) with 86%.
- Microsoft's Programming in HTML5 with JavaScript and CSS3 Specialist with 88%.
- Completed Complete Guide to Elasticsearch on Udemy.

Contributions to java community

- Writing on Java and JEE at http://thejavamonk.github.io/
- Contributions at Stack Overflow http://stackoverflow.com/users/2007325/praveen
- Contributions to open source projects on GitHub https://github.com/thejavamonk
- HackerRank profile https://www.hackerrank.com/thejavamonk

Bangalore 27, October 2016

(R. Praveen Kumar)